<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short discourse on the present temper of the nation with respect to the Indian and African company, and of the Bank of Scotland also, of Mr. Paterson's pretended fund of credit / by J.H.</title>
            <author>Holland, John, d. 1722.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44158</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2427</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6195</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12087452</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12087452</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53774</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44158)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53774)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 73:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short discourse on the present temper of the nation with respect to the Indian and African company, and of the Bank of Scotland also, of Mr. Paterson's pretended fund of credit / by J.H.</title>
                  <author>Holland, John, d. 1722.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Reid, and sold by Mrs. Beiglie ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: John Holland.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Paterson, William, 1658-1719.</term>
               <term>Company of Scotland Trading to Africa and the Indies.</term>
               <term>Bank of Scotland.</term>
               <term>Bank of England.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Commerce.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53774:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53774:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SHORT DISCOURSE ON THE Preſent Temper OF THE NATION With Reſpect to the INDIAN and AFRICAN Company; And of the BANK of SCOTLAND ALSO, Of Mr. <hi>Paterſon</hi>'s pretended <hi>Fund</hi> of <hi>Credit,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY J. H.</p>
            <p>EDINBURGH, Printed by <hi>John Reid,</hi> and Sold by Mrs. <hi>Beiglie,</hi> in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Cloſs, in the Year MDCXCVI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:53774:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53774:2"/>
            <head>To My LORD High CHANCELLOR, And the Remanent LORDS of His MAJESTIES Moſt Honourable Privy Council of the KINGDOM of SCOTLAND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORDS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WERE the Occaſion of my writting this ſmall Treatiſe, but Common and Indifferent, I would not have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to Addreſs Your Lordſhips, eſpecially being a Private Man, and of another Nation, but ſince the Greateſt Intereſts of the Kingdim are concerned in the Matter now in Diſpute, I hope your Lordſhips will not reckon me guilty of a Fault.</p>
            <p>It is well known to your Lordſhips, of what Importance the <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Trade is thought to be to this Nation, the number of the Subſcribers, and the quickneſs of the Subſcriptions, ſuppoſes Men have Great Expectations of its Succeſs, and it is become a Sign of Diſreſpect to the Common Good of the Kingdom, not to be concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it; Or at leaſt, not to Approve of it, and to pay a more than Ordinary Reſpect to the Projectors of it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:53774:3"/>
            <p>It is the Opinion of moſt Men, that this <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, will do the Nation very much Good, or very much Hurt, ſome expreſs it, That <hi>Scotland</hi> muſt either be Happy or very Unhappy, by the Succeſs thereof. It is indeed hard to tell the Event of Things in moſt Caſes, but in this, a Man but of Common Underſtanding, may give a Shrewd Gueſs, when the Beginnings of this Great Afair, is to the Prejudice, and upon the Plain Right of another Company, Conſtituted by the ſame King and Parliament, and is a Buſineſs which cannot hinder, but help all Trade.</p>
            <p>When Men have evil Deſigns, it is not hard to find out Plauſible Pretences to carry them on, tho for this of a <hi>Bank</hi> or <hi>Fund of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit,</hi> to be joyned to the <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Company, there never was leſs ſhew of Reaſon, for the Parliament have made the Act for the <hi>Bank,</hi> and the Act for the <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Company ſo diſtinct from one another, that there is all the Reaſon in the World, to Hope the <hi>Bank</hi> will be Incouraged and Protected.</p>
            <p>And ſince the Buſineſs of the <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Company, is for a Trade that your Lordſhips and the greateſt part of the Nation are not well Acquainted with; And alſo, becauſe the Setters up of this pretended <hi>Fund of Credit</hi> do miſrepreſent Things, I thought it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to direct this Diſcourſe to Your Lordſhips, that you may take more particular notice of the Matter in Diſpute, and diſcountenance what your Lordſhips ſhall think may tend to the Diſhonour and Prejudice of the Nation</p>
            <p>I will (with Your Lordſhips Favour) mention one Inſtance, which
<pb facs="tcp:53774:3"/>was offered to the Directors, and General Council of the <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Company at their laſt General Metting; <hi>To wit,</hi> That the <hi>Engliſh Eaſt Indian</hi> Companys, <hi>Caſhiers</hi> or <hi>Secrataris Notes,</hi> paſs currently in Payment for the Companys Uſe. My Lords, that this is not ſo, will appear upon due Enquiry, for I never ſaw or knew of any ſuch <hi>Notes,</hi> Altho I was about eight Years almoſt every day con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant in that Buſineſs, and for ſeveral Years ſince, have had Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to know the Affairs and Methods of that Company. And they are in the like Error in the Inſtances they give of other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies for Trade, on purpoſe to carry on their Deſign of a <hi>Bank,</hi> But ſince that the Stock of the <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Company, is ſo great a part of the whole Stock of the Nation, and that ſo much depends upon the Succeſs thereof, it is worthy Your Lordſhips Conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation (and that alſo of all others who Love their Countrey) whither theſe Mens Aſſertions are to be depended upon.</p>
            <p>The bare giving out that the <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Trade cannot be carried on without a <hi>Bank,</hi> or <hi>Fund of Credit,</hi> hath already pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed ſo far, That its thought by many the Excluſive Clauſe in the Act for the <hi>Bank,</hi> nor any thing elſe can ſtand in their way; But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho it could be proved, (which never can, or that their Project would any way help the <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African Trade</hi>) I will never believe, but that this Nation will have a due Regard to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith, And Apprehend the ſad Conſequences, not only to the <hi>Bank,</hi> but to the other Intereſts of the Kingdom, by the Breach thereof.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:53774:4"/>
            <p>However, For Vindicating the Juſtice of the Nation, and aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the <hi>Parliament,</hi> Your <hi>Lordſhips,</hi> and the <hi>Ordinary Court</hi> of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> will determine this Matter, according to the Plain Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Parliament in their Act for the Bank of <hi>Scotland,</hi> I am unkindly dealt by, yet I will not be diſcouraged to continue my Wiſhes and Endeavours for the Proſperity of this Kingdom, and at all times to approve my ſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My LORDS,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips, moſt Faithful, Humble Servant, JOHN HOLLAND.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53774:4"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE Concerning the INDIAN and AFRICAN COMPANY, And the BANK of SCOTLAND.</head>
            <p>THAT Trade and Comerce is an advantage to a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, or Comonwealth is ſo obvious to every under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Man, that there needs no Arguments to prove it, the Riches or Poverty of all places being uſually meaſured by the Increaſe or Decreaſe thereof.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conſider it, and but very Briefly under theſe two Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Heads. <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Trade that each Kingdom or Country hath within it ſelf, this we may call <hi>In-Land</hi> or <hi>Home-Trade.</hi> The Other is the Trade that one Kingdom or Country hath with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Kingdoms or Countries; This is Forraign Trade.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> of theſe is more or leſs in every Nation, nay, in every City and Town, and in thoſe Countries which produce what is neceſſary for the ſupport and Conveniency of its Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, a people even with this <hi>Home-Trade,</hi> may be Happy.</p>
            <p>The Forraign Trade is of two ſorts, One is the Trade that we have with other Countries, for what we conſume immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately our ſelves, without Tranſporting what we bring from thoſe places to other different Countries. This Trade is Profitable or prejudicial, according to the Value of what is ſent out and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53774:5"/>brought home; For it is Advantagious if the effects exported will ſell (where we carry them) for more than will pay for the Goods Imported, whereby the Remainder muſt be returned in Money. And it is unprofitable and a loſſing Trade, if what we Import coſts more than what we ſent out, whereby we muſt ſupply the Ballance with Money; So that this Forraign Trade in the one caſe is Advantagious, but in the other, will impoveriſh, and if this be conſidered as it ought to be, it is not only to drive a Forraign Trade and a great Trad. But to drive a Forraign Trade profitably, that deſerves encouragement, otherwayes we may be great loſſers thereby.</p>
            <p>The other ſort of Forraign Trade is, when what we Import from other Countries, either in whole or part, is ſent out again to other different places; This is as it were a double rrade, and may yield a double profit, if under an Honeſt and skilful man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement.</p>
            <p>To drive either one or both of theſe Forraign Trades, There ought to be great regard had to the Product of the Country from whence it is driven, whether it affoords matter ſufficient fit for other Countries; There ought to be Regard had to the hazard, and alſo that the Trade be not overdriven, but propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable to what the Nation is able to do, and many more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars ought to be conſidered in carrying on a Forraign Trade.</p>
            <p>Forraign Trade is carried on by particular Merchants, each for his own account as he is able, either in Purſe or Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, this is beſt in many caſes, and to ſome Nations the only ſafe way, the private Merchants being not under a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity to drive a Trade otherwayes than as they find it profitable.</p>
            <p>Forraign Trade by Companies in Joint Stocks, is alſo in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Caſes very neceſſary, but here there muſt be ſit Inſtruments, Men of Underſtanding (I Mean of Trade) Men of Honeſty and Application, theſe will preſcribe fair and wholſome methods, and will as fairly act thereby.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:53774:5"/>
            <p>There is an inconveniencie that attends a Companie, That the Money being raiſed, it puts them upon a kind of neceſſity of imploying the Stock, without a due Conſideration of all cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comſtances; And here I muſt go back and ſay, that there ought to be great Conſideration had in making a Company for Trade, to the Ability of the Nation, and quantity of the Stock, and many other things.</p>
            <p>The Inferences from the foregoing Aſſertions, I will not ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to make at this Time, tho I am ſatisfied they might be uſeful, and would be juſtified even in <hi>Scotland,</hi> by many Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and Wiſe Men at preſent, and by all the reſt that are Such, when the Hurry of the Great Affair now in Hand is over, or at leaſt, when the Succeſs of Things, ſhall diſcover the Truth or Falſehood of ſome Men's Pretentions; However, thus farr I will ſay, that Honeſty and Experience are eſſentially neceſſary for the carrying on a Company in a joint Stock.</p>
            <p>It hath been the Practice of all Wiſe Governments to Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the Subjects to Trade, and all things that might be for the Publict Benefit, by giving particular Priviledges either to ſingle Perſons or Companies, and that theſe Grants or Declarations have been depended upon by thoſe whom they were made to, is very well known by moſt Men: This plainly appears by the Pattents, Charters, and Acts, that are from time to time given particular Perſons and Companies, which would never be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, if there were no certain Dependance on the Faith and Juſtice of the Givers, and even in this Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> there are many ſuch publict Grants for the Encouragement of Trade, which I believe none will venture to ſay, that the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons concerned therein, have not had juſt Reaſon to believe, they ſhould enjoy the Priviledges mentioned in the ſaid Grants.</p>
            <p>A Breach of Faith, is not only baſe and unworthy, but it is alſo unprofitable and looſſing to the Breakers of it, and this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53774:6"/>is ſo even to private Perſons, but with this Difference, That in a private Caſe there may be Concealment, ſo the Scandal is not ſo great, and the Knavery dies with the Man. But all Mens Eyes are upon a Government, which ſurvives particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and ſo the Scandal and Loſs is the more publict and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</p>
            <p>There are few Men how wicked ſo ever they are, That would be willing to be publictly know to break their Promiſe, and when ſuch things are, it is generally denyed, and there are two Reaſons for it; The one is Reproach, which all the World over, is caſt upon ſuch People; And the other Reaſon is, That all People are Shie of them, and are afraid to have to do with them in any Matter whatſoever.</p>
            <p>If ſome will ſay there are Degrees in this Matter, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly is the Sin or Folly, more or leſs; That is, Where Faith is not plainly and directly broke, but Obliquely or in part; But this is all one, for the perſons wronged, are the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters of it, and ſo are all the Standers by. And in a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lict Caſe, the Nation wherein ſuch a thing is done, and alſo Neighbour Nations are Judges thereof.</p>
            <p>And in this matter I am confident, I ſhall not only have the Divine and the Chriſtian, but even the honeſt Heathen to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie what I ſay, and it will hold good in the moſt depraved Ages of the World, ſo that I will now come plainly to the Matter and Buſineſs in Queſtion. And in what I ſhall write, I will not knowingly do wrong to any Perſon, but endeavour to diſcourage and prevent the miſchiefs that ſome perſons by Ignorance or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, may do to this Kingdom, and a Body of Men, part of this Nation, and part in <hi>England,</hi> who entirely depending upon the Faith in an Act of the Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> have engaged in a Society for their own and for the Publict Benefit, and is a Buſineſs of ſuch a nature as interferrs with none, but helps all publict Undertakings, and under plain Open and Honeſt Rules and Methods.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:53774:6"/>
            <p>The Government of this Kingdom did think fit the laſt Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Parliament, To conſtitute two Companies. The one for an <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African Trade,</hi> and that none other ſhould for the ſpace of 31 years practiſe the ſame. This Act paſſed the 26th. <hi>June</hi> 1695. And the other for a <hi>Publict Bank,</hi> with an Exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Clauſe for the ſpace of 21 years. After the date thereof; In theſe words; <hi>And for the better Encouragement of the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany and Adventurers, It is hereby ſtatute, That the Joint Stock continuing in Money, ſhall be free from all Publict Burden, to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon Money, for the ſpace of</hi> 21 <hi>years, after the date hereof, And that during that ſpace it ſhall not be leaſome to any other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, To enter into and ſet up a diſtinct Company of Bank within this Kingdom, beſides theſe perſons allennarly into whoſe favours this Act is granted:</hi> Which Act paſſed the 17th <hi>July,</hi> following the other Act.</p>
            <p>After the Subſcriptions were made in both Nations, The Adventurers were pleaſed to chooſe me out of many much more worthy perſons, to be Governour of the Bank, and inveated me down to this Kingdom upon my own Charge and Expence, my Reward to be one tenth part of what profits ſhould be over and above 12 <hi>per Cent:</hi> Intereſt firſt to the Subſcrivers upon the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney payed into the ſeid Stock.</p>
            <p>Upon my Arrival, I immediatly began by all wayes that I could, to make the People underſtand the Nature of the Bank, and by what Rules and methods I ſhould offer to their conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration further to proceed by; And in the whole, I was plain and Candid without ſecret Equivacation or Noiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Principal Rules that I laid down, One was,</hi> That we muſt reduce the Intereſt at leaſt two <hi>per Cent:</hi> And that in all other reſpects we muſt make it as eaſie for the Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowers, as that they have liberty to pay in their Money at any
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53774:7"/>time they could after one Month, and alſo in parts. This was the Foundation of all, and whatever the Baſeneſs or Ignorance of ſome Men may inſinuate, in way of Reflection upon me, the Credit and Good of this alone will be Reputation to me, in the Opinion of Good and Wiſe Men, above the Vain Aplauſe that other Men have ſought; And as this was the great thing I aimed at in ſetting up the Bank, ſo I muſt alſo ſay, that it hath been the greateſt occaſion and riſe of all thoſe Deſigns and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to hurt and ruine the Bank, for thoſe whoſe Advantages are by Intereſt of Money, even at my very firſt mentioning my deſigne of Louring Intereſt, inſinuated among our own Friends by ſome plauſible Reaſons: So that every one of the Directors here for ſome time, was of a contrary Opinion to me in this particular. And ſince, ſeveral Sums of Money have been payed into their hands, by Perſons who have Borrowed of the Bank at four <hi>per Cent.</hi> They take all wayes whatſomever to defeat this Good and Great Undertaking.</p>
            <p>All the other Rules by which the Bank do Act are wholſome and plain, and not only in the Notion, But in the practice of them; ſo that on all hands they are approved of.</p>
            <p>So ſoon as the Rules and Methods for carrying on the Bank, were agreed to by the Generall Meeting of the Adventurers, The Directors proceeded to buſineſs, and with ſuch ſucceſs that the Credit of the Bills, as faſt as they were iſſued out, obtained to a degree beyond expectation, and the Bank had Univerſal Applauſe, except now and then an angry word from a few Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, money'd men, for the reaſons aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>The <hi>African</hi> and <hi>Indian</hi> Company at the ſame time, had Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions to near four hundred thouſand pound <hi>Sterling. By</hi> (if I miſtake not) about 1500 perſons ſome of the payments of the One Quarter part ſo ſoon as the Bank was open, were made by Direction of the Mannagers of that Subſcription in the Bank, Each Society thanking the other, the One for the trouble it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53774:7"/>ſaved them, and the Other for the confidence repoſed in them.</p>
            <p>And as for Perſonal Civilities between Mr. <hi>Paterſon</hi> and my ſelf, they were ſuch, as there was to my knowledge no thought or Proſpect of any difference, for I neither wrote nor ſpoke to any Body of what I obſerved, only took the freedom of think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Till about the middle of <hi>May,</hi> There was a Rumor of a deſign for ſetting up a Fund of Credit, by the <hi>African</hi> Company; I was indeed ſurprized thereat, and when I had informed my ſelf in the Matter, I could not but exclaim againſt the folly and diſhoneſty of the deſign, and charge the ſame upon the perſons that ſhould be the Contrivers thereof.</p>
            <p>I gave my Friends in <hi>England</hi> two Poſts after this diſcovery, an account of what I had underſtood of this matter tho the Poſt before ſeveral Perſons had done the ſame, and they and all others who heard of it, were as much ſurpriſed as my ſelf, and ſome who had Subſcribed to the <hi>Africa Company,</hi> forbid their Agents paying any Money into the Stock, as unſatisfied and ſcandelized at this deſign.</p>
            <p>Moſt people here alſo, tho nowayes concerned in the Bank, but only in the <hi>Africa</hi> Company, exclaimed againſt this new project as a matter unjuſt, unſafe, and on all ſides prejudicial, and as what was nothing like either what the Act Imported, (being ſolely for a Forraign Trade and Comerce,) or what any of the ſaid Subſcribers to the <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Company had ever a thought of.</p>
            <p>This reſentment from all perſons, made ſuch an impreſſion on the perſons that contrived and carried on this deſign of a <hi>Fund of Credit,</hi> that it was denyed and evaded by all manner of Art, and I was blamed for believing of it, becauſe the Directors of that Company, except four or five immediately concerned, knew nothing of it, however they went on, and every day it became more and more publict, and it is now the great and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53774:8"/>ſubject of every ones thoughts and diſcourſe throughout the whole Nation.</p>
            <p>It is urged, That Mr. <hi>Paterſon</hi> deſigned a Bank even at firſt in the <hi>Indian</hi> &amp; <hi>African</hi> Act, &amp; becauſe the Act in the whole Scope thereof is wholly for Trade, he would prove his Deſign by a Letter, which it will be neceſſary to give ſome Account of.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Thomas Deans</hi> having given the Draught of the Act for the Bank, which he had from me, unto ſome Lawyer, to put into the <hi>Scots</hi> Stile, ſome One of the Gentlemen, who came from <hi>London</hi> to Solitite the <hi>African</hi> Act, accidentally ſaw the ſaid Draught for the Bank on the Lawyers Dask, and being ſurprized that ſuch a thing ſhould be without their knowing any thing of it, or from whom it came, they immediately wrote to Mr. <hi>Paterſon</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> thinking it muſt be from him, he being ſo famous for ſetting up of Banks, and therein compleaning of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs, that he did not acquaint them thereof. On the other ſide, Mr. <hi>Paterſon</hi> was as much ſurpriſed at their Letter, and returned Anſwer, that it was all ſtrange to him, but deſired them by all means to make what intereſt in Parliament they could againſt it, for that he deſigned a Bank as a part of the <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Buſineſs.</p>
            <p>When I heard of this Letter, and what Mr. <hi>Pathrſon</hi> had Anſwered to it, I accoſted him with a litle ſort of Briskneſs, and asked him how he could pretend to know any thing of the nature of a Bank, if he thought it could be joyned with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Buſineſs, and his Anſwer was, <hi>That he was only afraid that it would prejudice the</hi> Indian <hi>Company;</hi> For otherwayes he had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſay againſt the Bank. And before I came for <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſome of his Friends deſired me that I would carry my ſelf Civilly to him, and upon my Arival he came to me, and Begged me Pardon for ever pretending againſt the Bank, and that what ever had been, was only for fear it might interrupt and hinder the Subſcriptions to the <hi>Africa</hi> Company, but he ſaw it did not, and therefore wiſhed all manner of Succeſs to it,</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:53774:8"/>
            <p>And now to paliate this unworthy Deſign of Setting up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Bank, he and his Friends, would pretend a Kind of Right, becauſe he ſaid in his Letter, as is before narrated, but where the Senſe of this Aſſertion made by himſelf, and ſeveral Others is, I do not think any Body can ſee.</p>
            <p>For if he had Originally a Deſign to make the Bank a part of his, I: and A: Company, Wherefore did he not couch his Act ſomething ſuteably? And why did he not tell the Deſign to thoſe, unto whom alone he diſcovered the <hi>African</hi> and <hi>Indian</hi> Affair? And if he'le ſay he did, tell them? Even his very Friends muſt not believe him, For Mr. <hi>Chiſelies</hi> Letters, and his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn ſpeaks them abſolutely ignorant of it, and his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion to me in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> before Several, That he was only afraid the Bank might hinder the Subſcription to the <hi>African</hi> Company, declares the ſame.</p>
            <p>It is further inſinuated, as a Reaſon for this Deſign, that they have not preſent uſe for their Money in their Trade, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ought not to ly idle; And in this particular there will appear neither Senſe nor good Husbandry, if we conſider that they allowed <hi>Twelve per Cent</hi> for prompt Payment, to get the Money in.</p>
            <p>But with this we muſt conſider that at the ſame time they urge very ſtrenuouſly an other Argument, and which they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ought &amp; ſhall prevail, &amp; in Truth is the greateſt that they can offer, and is very popular, it is this, that without a Bank or Fund of Credit, an <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Trade cannot be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on, and that Companies of Trade in other places, have ſuch Banks or Funds of Credit; But this is both ridiculous and untrue; For do they not urge it as an Argument for this deſign? That they have ſo much Money more than they can uſe for ſome time, That it will be a great loſs not to lend it out; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, how can this <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Trade ſo want a Bank joyned to it for the carrying it on, while but a ſmall part of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53774:9"/>Subſcription is too much to be employed for ſome conſiderable time; Are there not 1500 Adventurers to call money from? And in ſuch proportions and times, better than can be from perſons who they lend their Money to. Beſides, their aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is untrue: For Companies ſet up for Trade and Comerce in other Countries, have not Banks and Funds of Credit belonging to them; But the matter lyes plainly here, that tho they have nothing of Truth, Reaſon, or Honeſty to help them on in this Bank project; Yet they have this great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, that the <hi>African</hi> and <hi>Indian</hi> Trade is of ſuch Value and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem, in the Opinion even of all Men in General in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; That whateven is offered by Mr. <hi>Paterſon</hi> to further it, is received with applauſe, without any inquity into the Truth of what he ſaith.</p>
            <p>And upon this account, As a Fund of Credit is believed to foreward the <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Trade, it is a hard matter with many at this time to judge whether all the Right of the Bank of <hi>Scotland,</hi> (ſo plainly founded by a moſt expreſs and Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive excluſive clauſe for twenty one years) ſhall not be Invaded and trampled upon, tho to the Eternal Scandle of the Nation. And all this I ſay, becauſe it is pretended (but not Proved nor can be) That a Bank or Fund of Credit is neceſſary, and will encourage the <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Trade.</p>
            <p>When I came down to <hi>Scotland,</hi> which was the 18th of <hi>March</hi> I found Mr. <hi>Paterſon</hi> very popular, and in ſome proportion Mr. <hi>Smith</hi> and Mr. <hi>Lodg,</hi> and I found the whole Nation ſo Univerſally in favour of this <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Trade, that altho I obſerved ſeveral things in my Opinion very odd and ſtrange, and heard frequently things urged that I could no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve to be true, as that Buſineſs and Trade is ſo and ſo carried on in other Nations; Yet I thought it both Prudence and good Manners not to contradict the Common Opinion of the Nation; And I had gone away as quietly, if Mr. <hi>Paterſon</hi> had followed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53774:9"/>his own proper buſineſs (tho by Wayes and Methods right or wrong) by which he had ſo highly raiſed the Expectation of the People; And from which buſineſs, without ſo much as a thought of a Fund of Credit, the Subſcrivers had their Hopes of Profit.</p>
            <p>But ſince that, inſtead of going about their Forraign Trade, they firſt intend to trip up the heels of another Company, ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from theirs, ſo fairly eſtabliſhed upon ſuch good Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods and Rules, and upon a plain Right even in the Opinion of all the World, I may very well be excuſed, Nay, it may be thought my Duty, to expoſe the Evil of a Deſign ſo unjuſt, and every way tending to Miſchief and Confuſion.</p>
            <p>I am under a great Diſadvantage, in what I can ſay, againſt the proceedings of theſe Men, by the Baſe and Falſe Reports that are raiſed of me. <hi>That I am a Spye from the</hi> England Eaſt-Indian <hi>Company, and came down here to ruine the</hi> Indian <hi>and</hi> Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can <hi>Company of</hi> Scotland, <hi>That I have a Penſion or Fee from the</hi> Engliſh Eaſt-Indian <hi>Company, to do what I can againſt the</hi> Scots <hi>Compay.</hi> The bare Aſſertion prevails with many, but to give the Report Authority, It is ſaid, <hi>A Perſon of Quality had a Letter a little time after I came from</hi> England, <hi>that I came down here to oppoſe the</hi> Scots Indian <hi>and</hi> African <hi>Company.</hi> They alſo Report, That I ſhould ſay, <hi>I would prevail upon the Parliament of</hi> England <hi>to Ruine this Company.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed I am aſhamed that there ſhould be any occaſion to mention thoſe very ridiculous Stories; But ſuch is the Zeal of the Nation to the <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Trade, that many are thereby prejudiced againſt me; And becauſe they cannot An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer what I have argued againſt their Deſign, they tell one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, We muſt not believe what Mr. <hi>Holland</hi> ſayeth, for he is an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man, and ingaged in a direct contrary Intereſt.</p>
            <p>They report me in other Reſpects very falſely, and all to take away the Credit of any thing I may ſay; And it is become dangerous for a Man to expreſs his Thoughts freely of this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53774:10"/>Matter, People being under more Awe and Fear, of giving their Opinion of the <hi>African</hi> and <hi>Indian</hi> Company, both as to the Projectors, and the Method they are fallen into. Then ever I remember the <hi>Diſſentors</hi> in a Former Reign, and the <hi>Jacobites</hi> in this, were of ſpeaking againſt the Government; Not that the Laws of the Kingdom do any way reſtrain People, but the Danger is from an univerſal Prejudice, that is immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly contracted againſt any that Speak or Do, what hath but the leaſt ſhew of Diſcouragement to this Forraign Trade, and this without ever Examining whither what is ſaid, is in Reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or not, the Truth of this, all the Nation are Witneſſes of.</p>
            <p>I never thought to have appeared in Print, I have not a capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city for it as other men, nor do I affect noiſe or being taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, and at this time, I am under a further diſadvantage, becauſe the Buſineſs I came about, to wit, the Bank, takes up my time; But ſince providence hath engaged me in this publick Undertaking of the Bank; And that this other deſign hath by the folly and wickedneſs of ſome few perſons, fallen ſo unhappily to interferr with the Bank, &amp; in ſuch a nature, as that the Kingdom may be concerned thereby in its greateſt entereſts, <hi>I</hi> reckon it my duty to do what <hi>I</hi> can to prevent the miſchiefs that this Nation will fall into, if this humor be not timely taken off, and <hi>I</hi> heartily Pray GOD, to open the Eyes of theſe people, and encline them to conſider of what dangerous. Conſequence it is to Invade a plain Right, and bear down by noiſe and force, Truth, Reaſon, Order, and all that is Sacred.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> have many Witneſſes of Honeſt and Worthy Men, That <hi>I</hi> have alwiſe thought it the Intereſt of <hi>England</hi> to have this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Happy and Flouriſhing. And for what is ſo baſely inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated and ſpread Abroad, of my being a Spy, &amp; comming down to dſcourage this Company, is both falſe and ridiculous, and the fame are all the other Aſperſions.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:53774:10"/>
            <p>For from my firſt being here, in all Companies <hi>I</hi> came into, <hi>I</hi> declared that <hi>I</hi> was ſworn to the <hi>Engliſh Eaſt Indian</hi> Company; That ſo no man might talke any thing before me, that he thought <hi>I</hi> would or could take an advantage of againſt their <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Company, and <hi>I</hi> abhore the thoughts of ſo mean and baſe an Undertaking, tho <hi>I</hi> have and ever will pay all manner of reſpect to that Society of the <hi>Engliſh Eaſt Indian</hi> Company I have been concerned in.</p>
            <p>And for what they untruely ſay, I ſpoke of making an Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt with the Parliament, I am aſhamed to think any ſuch thing, both becauſe I would not have any Body believe, I am ſo vaine to value my ſelf at ſuch a Rate; And alſo, becauſe I would have this People know, The Parliament of <hi>England</hi> is infinitly too great to be influenced by any particular Perſon whatſover, and much leſs by ſuch a privat Man as I am; And I am ſure that I have ſhewn theſe People that make ſuch a Bluſter in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by my own Carriage, an Example of Humility, and of the Duty and Reſpect due to the Government.</p>
            <p>Nor do I value any thing of this kind with Reſpect to my ſelf, ſince ſome of theſe Men have had the Boldneſs, to caſt as untrue a Reflection upon a Noble Lord, the Earl <hi>Rocheſter, viz:</hi> That he ſhould publictly Tare and Trample upon the <hi>African</hi> and <hi>Indian</hi> Company's Act of Parliament; which was current a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all People, till my Lord <hi>Tarbat</hi> came from <hi>England,</hi> and did my Lord <hi>Rocheſter</hi> Juſtice, by declaring how much of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Temper his Lordſhip was of, with Reſpect to this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            <p>I do indeed value the good Opinion of Men, but it is of Wiſe and Honeſt Men, and not upon a meer Shew and Noiſe, but from Fact from what I do that may really deſerve Eſteem. The Buſineſs <hi>I</hi> only came here about, was to ſet up the Bank, which is upon an Honeſt Foot, and carryed on by plain and rational Methods; Not by little Tricks, but in ſuch
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53774:11"/>a way, that all who know the Bank and its Methods, do at firſt ſight ſee the Reaſonableneſs and Fairneſs of them, and theſe expoſed to all People from the very firſt, All having been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with due Conſideration by the Court of Directors, and then fairly Offered to the Conſideration of the General Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for their Sanction.</p>
            <p>It may be thought by ſome, that <hi>I</hi> ſay all this only to ſave the Bank, for that <hi>I</hi> am ſo much concerned in the intereſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but <hi>I</hi> do not. <hi>I</hi> have other as great reaſons that I Write this for, and more Juſt and Hanourable than theſe men will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver act upon, let them pretend what they will, <hi>Viz.</hi> The Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and wellſare of the Kingdom, which theſe Men wound, and if not ſtopped in their proceedings, will lay in the duſt.</p>
            <p>I have all along ſaid, The Parliament of this Kingdom will keep their Faith, they know it is juſt, and they know it their intrreſt ſo to do.</p>
            <p>Specious pretences will not prevail upon ſo Wiſe an Aſſembly, Order and Truth muſt be mantained, elſe all will go to confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and the deareſt intereſts of the Kingdom will ſuffer to ſuch a degree as will make the Nation diſpiſed, and hated all the World over.</p>
            <p>We have no reaſon to be affraid of the multitude of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Concerned in the <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Company; For even if they were Judges, if they will but conſider things, they will abhore this attempt, invented and carried on by a few, for a little pretendeds (tho not really one Farthing) profit, to the hazard of the Honour of the Happineſs of the Nation.</p>
            <p>Thoſe little tricks and evaſions, calling it a Fond of Credit. and not a Bank, the Clauſe in the <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Act of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving their Stock to the beſt advantage, and the nonſenſical and untrue aſſertion, that a Forraign trade in a joynt Stock can not be caried on to Advantage, without a Bank or Fund of Credit (which is not ſo in other Kingdoms; For Companis of Forraign
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53774:11"/>Trade, borrow, not lend Money) and all the reſt of that Stuff will never prevail, and I am throughly perſwaded not only of this, but that a ſad fate will attend theſe men, who begin their Buſineſs with ſo many falſe and unheard of inſinuations and practices.</p>
            <p>It is Untrue and Ridiculous, what they make this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to believe, of the Wayes and Methods of other Kingdoms, in carrying on a Forraign Trade, if Enquiry be made. Where are the Companys for Forraign Trade that lend their money? I'm ſure there are none in <hi>England,</hi> but that's not to be valued, the prejudice is ſo great to <hi>England,</hi> that their Example is not to be followed even in Trade: But the Truth is, becauſe it is neareſt this Kingdom, and if they go not further, they will be ſoon diſcovered. <hi>I</hi> dare not ſay, (tho its true) That in <hi>Holland</hi> and other places, Companies for Trade are carried on without lending money; And having Funds and Banks of Credit be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the ſaid Companies, I ſay it is giving them an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, if <hi>I</hi> talk of what is done in theſe Kingdoms, becauſe, if <hi>Mr. Patenſon</hi> will aſſert the contrary, it muſt be believed. Never was ſuch an implicite Faith before, in a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            <p>As for the Methods and Conſtitutions of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies in my own Countrey; This Kingdom, as <hi>I</hi> before hinted, is too much prejudiced by what the Parliament did with reſpect to this deſign, to take any Example by them for carrying on the <hi>African</hi> and <hi>Indian</hi> Trade, tho no Rational <hi>Man</hi> can ſee a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it; <hi>I</hi> alſo will be ſilent as to other things in this great Conſtitution, But ſo far <hi>I</hi> will ſay, That let ſome Men but give themſelves Names, they are thought to have ſuteable Qualifications, as Mr. <hi>Lodge</hi> and Mr. <hi>Camphel</hi> eſteem'd among many the Top Merchants in this great Affair. But why do <hi>I</hi> queſtion theſe Mens Abilities? Is it not poſſible that they ſhould by inſpiration, ſince they came from <hi>England,</hi> have
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53774:12"/>ſome Extraordinary Gifts for Trade, more than ever they had before?</p>
            <p>I cannot Argue upon this matter as <hi>I</hi> would, not only for want of time, but alſo becauſe <hi>I</hi> muſt not inſtance any thing how true ſo ever, of what is done in other places, For then <hi>I</hi> am laid upon my back, becauſe theſe Men will deny that any ſuch things are; And therefore <hi>I</hi> muſt diſcourſe ſo, and inſtance things that may here in this place be known to be true, from theſe Mens own Confeſſion, and from the Nature of the things themſelves.</p>
            <p>It is then known and confeſſed, That Mr. <hi>Paterſon</hi> was to have a ſmmm of Money for his Service to the Bank of <hi>England,</hi> He ſaith, <hi>It was for being the Founder and Setter up of the ſaid Bank;</hi> It is alſo confeſſed, he had not the Reward. The ſame in every particular of the Orphans Fund, Only in the laſt, he hath ſome Aſſurance to have 5 <hi>per Cent</hi> of the Profites: And further, It is known, That there was an Agreement to have 2 <hi>per Cent</hi> out of the Stock of the <hi>African</hi> and <hi>Indian</hi> Company, even without running any hazard, or ſtaying for the Succeſs of the thing: And that he afterwards relinquiſhed this Bargain of the 2 <hi>per Cent,</hi> this is all known and confeſſed.</p>
            <p>Now let us Fairly, (tho not Fully) examine this matter, And Firſt, What may be thought the Reaſon that the Bank of <hi>England</hi> did not give Mr. <hi>Paterſon</hi> the Reward? It is ſaid on one ſide, <hi>Becauſe he baſely betrayed them:</hi> But by him, <hi>That they were unjuſt, &amp;c.</hi> But which is to be believed, Whither the 26 Directors, Men of Eſtate, and Men of Eſteem, or Mr. <hi>Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon?</hi> Let every Body judge as they pleaſe. I will only ſay in it ſo much, That he is believed in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and they in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> And I will obſerve this, That what ever we thought of Mr. <hi>Paterſon</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> (and I ſpeak it without Detracting from the Merit of thoſe Worthy Gentlemen of the Bank of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>) he is in this Kingdom looked upon to be a Wiſer Man,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53774:12"/>and is abundantly more Popular here, than all that Court of Directors, or the Governour Deputy, and 24 Committee Men of the <hi>Engliſh Eaſt-Indian</hi> Company are in <hi>England;</hi> Elſe why ſuch a buſle all the Kingdom over, and ſo many New wayes for the ſetting up a Company for a Forraign Trade, and by an implicite Faith in Mr. <hi>Paterſons</hi> Judgement and Honeſtie.</p>
            <p>In the next place, we may enquire and tell what Opinion both Nations have of his ſetting up the <hi>Orphans Fund,</hi> in this Kingdom it is all well, and an Act of Merit and great ingenuity, But in <hi>England</hi> it is looked upon the Direct contrary; And as one great occaſion of the preſent miſeries in the Kingdom; As for my Particular Opinion in this Matter. I confeſs what ſome have charged me with, that I ſhould ſay, If I had a Brother that ſhould ſet up one Bank againſt another; and if I were Judge, I would hang him for his pains; Not that <hi>I</hi> would charge the many Honeſt and ingenuous Gentlemen in that Fund, as Adventurers or Directors of a Crime; For there was in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> no Reſtriction by Law nor Cuſtome, but moſt of them were Ignorant of what the Conſequences might be; But if the Bank of <hi>England</hi> had been ſo happy to have had an Excluſive Clauſe, none would have dared to Offer that Affront to the Parliament, ſo much as to talk of ſetting up another Bank.</p>
            <p>In the Third place, We may conſider what Love and Zeal there was in this Gentleman, and ſome of his Friends, for the good of his Countrey, in ſetting up this <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Company in <hi>Scotland;</hi> it is indeed thought a great Deal; But even <hi>Scotland</hi> it ſelf, who ſo Adore him, muſt confeſs that till he came down here, the Great Certain and Preſent Reward (the Twelve Thouſand pounds Sterling out of the Subſcription) was equal to the Zeal for his Countrey Mens Good; And by others it will be believed, The Money was much more the Cauſe of that Generous Paſſion: I cannot but ſmile, while I am writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this Paragraph, how very well this is taken by many in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53774:13"/>this Kingdom, whom if they conſider and compare, Times and Things, its as plain as a Mathematical Demoſtration, that there was ſelf enough in the Caſe, And that he had carved for himſelf and his Abettors, without any Hazard, a Bountiful Portion of the Six Hundred Thouſand Pound <hi>African</hi> Stock; But he hath Relinquiſhed, and ſtands now to the Juſtice and Generoſity of the Company, Or at leaſt of the Counſel and Directions of the Company; Of which I will ſay a Word or two, And it is,</p>
            <p>That I obſerve, not a Voluntary Act as to the Will, that Mr. <hi>Paterſon</hi> gave up the 2 <hi>per Cent,</hi> but by a down-right neceſſity, or elſe all muſt ſtop; And if I miſtake not in this particular, the <hi>Scots</hi> People were chiefly the Occaſion of his Relinguiſhing this certain Reward.</p>
            <p>But now he thinks he hath contrived matters for his advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, better, He hath turned things into a never before ſeen method; And ſo many engagements are laid upon particular perſons, that thoſe and he together hope to manage the Council and Directors, ſo as the thing may ſome way make good the former diſapointment, but they are moſt of them Worthy Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, and will not long be carried away by words without Correſpondent actions.</p>
            <p>Men will in time conſider the Juſtice and Equity of things, and their intereſt in Reality, The publick &amp; plauſible name of a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Trade, oppoſed ſo much by the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and (tho untruely and fooliſhly ſaid) by me on purpoſe from the <hi>Engliſh Eaſt Indian</hi> Company, will not keep the Nation long in a belief that this matter muſt be as great and profitable as is talked; For as I ſaid before, it is not only to drive a Forraign Trade and a great Trade, but to drive a profitable Trade, that will be the advantage of this Kingdom, and all the World will Confeſs, that ſuch an undertaking ſhould be begun and carried on by Rules of Juſtice and Prudence.</p>
            <p>But what's the very firſt ſcene of this project, Truely another
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53774:13"/>Bank or <hi>Fund of Credit,</hi> without any pretence to any ſuch thing, and without the leaſt expectation of it from any of the Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers in the <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Company, there being not ſix Men among the whole Subſcribers, that can ſay they had a thought of any ſuch deſign when they Subſcribed, and upon the firſt notice of it, there was an Univerſal ſurprize, Theſe are bad beginnings of a Forraign Trade, orany other Undertaking. I dare not write ſo freely, as if people were not by falſe &amp; baſe inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions prejudiced againſt me; However I will ſay, that there is in theſe men a great deale of folly and injuſtice, and I have no reaſon to fear that it will be believed to be picque, what I have ſaid of theſe men, as ſome (by not knowing how things are carried on,) have thought, I Thank GOD, as I did formerly to Mr. <hi>Paterſon,</hi> forgive ſeveral injuries, ſo I can and will do again, upon thoſe terms that any Honeſt Man in the World will judge I ought to do it.</p>
            <p>I Appeal to thoſe Gentlemen of the Subſcribers only to the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Company, whether Mr. <hi>Paterſon</hi> and ſome others have not ſometimes denyed. and ſometimes evaded all theſe matters, and even the ſame dayes and Hours in Company of thoſe they thought would, like their project of a Fund of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit have confeſſed they would carry it on, and ſeveral perſons of Honour as not Countenancing it were made to think, that all would go over, and that nothing ſhould be done to interfer with the Bank of <hi>Scotland;</hi> Will any man then of Senſe and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty ſay, this proceeding is plain, Candid and fair. And will any Wiſe and good Men think here is Honeſty enough to carry on a buſineſs for the Credit and good of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Is there no Regard to Honour in this Nation, Nor to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intereſts of it, that all ſhall be thrown down by the popular Argument or aſſertion, that an <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Trade will be a good thing to the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>I am told frequently that I loſe ground in the opinion of many,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53774:14"/>and that ſpeaking againſt theſe proceedings endangers the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Bank, I thank my Friends for the Kindneſs intended thereby, but the Bank ſtands not upon ſuch a Foundation, as any thing of this nature can hurt it, it is a good thing to the Nation for the Encouraging of Trade, for the Lands, and for the eaſe of people in diſtreſs, and under heavy burthens of debt by Money'd Men, to ſome of whom we owe in a great meaſure the occaſion of all this, and who are continually labouring to deſtroy the Bank by this interferring theſe hallow on both ſides, and hope (and notwithout good grounds) That theſe unjuſt proceedings of Mr. <hi>Paterſons</hi> project for a Fund of Credit, ſhall bring matters to ſuch a paſs, that no Trade ſhall be ſo great as Uſury.</p>
            <p>Are there no inſtances in this Nation of miſchief by very much leſſer diſorders in buſineſs than this is, and ſhall they be totally forgotten, nor will there be no reflections made upon the diſtreſſes of <hi>England</hi> on this Account, <hi>Goldſmiths</hi> and <hi>Banks,</hi> fighting one againſt another, its impoſſible but men will ſee it their intereſt and duty to prevent the miſchiefs in plain view.</p>
            <p>I will not believe that the Crafty inſinuations of theſe men will prevail in the Parliament, in the Council, or in any Court of Juſtice, nothing of that which they urge, and which they deceive ſo many Honeſt Gentlemen by, <hi>Viz:</hi> Have they not power to lend their Money, may not people take their Notes, will top the reaſon and Juſtice of thoſe wife Aſſemblies, where is the Senſe of giving their Notes? And where is the profit, if it be not in the way of a Bank? And would it not then be an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front to the Parliament, Council or Court of Juſtice to think that theſe litle tricks ſhall prevail?</p>
            <p>Doth not Religion preſcribe Rules of Equity, and muſt all Principles which even Natural Reaſon teacheth, give way and be trampled under foot, upon pretence that his Fund of Credit helps the <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Trade? Or muſt it be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53774:14"/>the Gentleman, upon having an account from <hi>Scotland</hi> of my draught of the Act for the Bank, was pleaſed to write to Mr. <hi>Chieſly</hi> that he ſhould hinder its paſſing, for that he intended a Bank in his <hi>Africa</hi> Act? Or is it becauſe of the Clauſe in the <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Act, that they may imploy their Stock to the beſt advantage.</p>
            <p>If the Nation think the <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Trade Valuable, and that Mr. <hi>Paterſon</hi> and his two or three friends are ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the carrying it on, let them proceed as they ſhall ſee cauſe, the Adventurers will be contented very well, without their encroachment on others, and they will not deſire to gain by indirect practices, they never thought of this Fund of Credit that is now trumpt up. Good GOD! where are theſe mens Honeſty in this deſign? I will ſay, let them pretend and Cant as they pleaſe, there will be no profit, but loſs and confuſion in it; as may eaſily be proved, and ſhall be, if they acknowledge in Print the true reaſon of their proceeding.</p>
            <p>I hope my Friends and Partners in the Bank, will not fear any Danger, my loſs will be aboundantly greater than any of theirs, And if theſe People ſhould prevail, which I cannot any wayes be perſwaded to think; Yet I will in ſuch caſe, ſhew an Example of Patience, and Lament chiefly the ſad Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences it will have upon the whole Nation.</p>
            <p>The Breach of a Promiſe, Reflects a Scandal upon a private Perſon, ſo as to make him Odious to all that believe it of him; What then will be the Shame and Scandal to a Nation, If the Publick Faith be broken? For as I hinted before in this caſe, it is not the Perſons injured, and the Perſons that do the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, that do only take Notice of, and will be the Judges of the Matter; But all the People of the ſame Kingdom, and of the Neighbour Nations likewiſe, let it then be far from us to think that the <hi>Parliament, Council</hi> or <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Juſtice</hi> will not protect us againſt all theſe Mens Arts and power.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:53774:15"/>
            <p>Indeed I muſt confeſs that a blind Zeal for Religion, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and many times Intereſt of State, hath occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned the breach of the Publick Faith, this Latter frequently among the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Infidels.</hi> But it is hardly to be found, that ever the Publick Faith which hath been given for (what we are diſcourſing of) Trade, was ever broke even by the worſt of Men. And if there can be any Examples given in this kind, it is ſo farr from being juſtified, that (with one Voice) all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple would cry out upon it as baſe and unjuſt, and as what would infallibly be an abſolute Barr and Diſcouragement to People for ever after to Addreſs the Publick.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
